Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is קל"ט, Kuf Lamed
Tet, בבא בתרא Bava Batra 139, and we pick up on the
משנה Mishnah at the very bottom of קל"ח עמוד ב', Kuf Lamed
Chet Amud Bet, and we're dealing with a case about a father
who transfers property to his son and that he really wants his
son to be able to take full possession and use of it
only after he dies, the father dies. So he gives the גוף
מהיום ופירות לאחר מיתה, guf me-hayom u-peirot le-achar mita, that the son
technically owns the title now, so therefore it's not going to be
a problem of a gift that only takes place after death, but
the son only comes into the rights of benefiting from all of
the produce of the field after the father dies. And let's take
a look at what the case of the משנה Mishnah is. So
it says: האב תולש ומאכיל לכל מי שירצה,
Ha-av tolesh u-ma'achil le-chol
mi she-yirtzeh,
as long as the father is still alive, the father still has
rights to the fruit from the field, so the father can go
ahead and harvest the fruit and give it to whoever he wants,
the son has no claim on that. ומה שהניח תלוש, u-ma she-hiniach
talush,
and if the father after harvested it, and then the father dies,
so
once the father harvested it, that's the father's fruit, and now then
he dies, and the son gets title, excuse me, already had title,
gets right to the fruit that's going to grow, but the fruit
that already was grown and harvested, that belongs to the father, and
therefore the הלכה halacha is: הרי הוא של יורשים, harei hu shel
yorshim, that goes to all of the heirs, not this particular child
that he gave this field to. So the גמרא Gemara says: תלוש
אין מחובר לא. talush in mechubar lo. So that makes it very
clear that the father only keeps what he already harvested but not
what grew from the land. And that's not necessarily so logical, right?
Because if the father has the rights to the פירות, peirot, then
as the fruit is growing even before it's harvested, you would think
that that's owned by the father. But nevertheless, the משנה Mishnah says
that it implies that if the father dies before it's been harvested,
that that is considered to be transfers to this particular son, not
all of the heirs. Okay, but let's take a look. והתניא, Ve-hatanya,
but we taught in a ברייתא Baraitha top of, excuse me, והתניא,
ve-hatanya, yes, top of קל"ח עמוד א', Kuf Lamed Chet Amud Aleph,
we taught in a ברייתא: Baraitha: שמין את המחוברים ללוקח, shamin et
ha-mechubarim la-lokeach,
that if this son goes ahead and in turn while the father's
alive sells this to a third party and
then and then the father dies, then you assess the value of
the fruit that's still on the tree and this purchaser, right, the
purchaser who's now in the place of the son who would have
taken it, the purchaser who now comes into possession of not only
the title but the rights to the פירות, peirot, he has to
pay back the heirs for the fruit that's on the tree. All
right, so that's basically shows it's exactly our case except take out
the son and have it that the son sold to another party,
and it says that the fruit that's on the tree still belongs
to the father. If they belong to the father when it grew
and when the father dies it passes on to all the heirs.
So how do you reconcile that with our משנה? Mishnah? So the
גמרא Gemara says: אמר עולא לא קשיא כאן בבנו כאן באחר. Amar
Ulla lo kashya kan be-veno kan be-acher. So no, that's the difference.
The difference is whether we're dealing with the son or with a
somebody who's not a son. דעתו של אדם קרובה אצל בנו, da'ato
shel adam kerova etzel beno, that even though the father really does
have rights to the fruit while the father is alive and the
son only has title and therefore logically the fruit on the tree
really should belong to the father, and that is the case when
we're talking about a third party, not the son, that the third
party only gets the right to the fruit after the father dies,
but when we're dealing with the son himself, the father wants him
to have even the fruit on the tree and therefore that is
the case of our משנה Mishnah that the father only gets possession
of the fruit once it is harvested. Okay, let's take a look
now at a totally different case, next משנה, Mishnah, top of קל"ט
עמוד א'. Kuf Lamed Tet Amud Aleph. הניח בנים גדולים וקטנים אין
הגדולים מתפרנסים על ידי קטנים ולא קטנים ניזונים על הגדולים.
Hiniach banim gedolim u-ketanim ein ha-gedolim mitparnasim al yedei ketanim ve-lo ketanim
nizonim al ha-gedolim.
So somebody dies, leaves an estate and you have a lot of
sons and some are older and some are younger,
say five years old, three years old and then you have people
twenty years old, twenty-five years old, and so what you so this
estate is equally owned by all of them and you should divide
it up and everybody should get their portion. But you know, you
don't always get around to dividing the estate right away. So can
you just go ahead and say
that the food bill will come off of the whole estate and
it'll just be deducted from the entirety of the estate and when
you get to dividing it, you'll divide what's left? Or how about
the bill for clothing? Right, everybody's clothing needs you'll just take it
from the entire estate. So there's a problem with that because the
food needs are greater for the kids than for the adults. It's
generally assumed that there's more waste and whatever so for small children
there's higher food costs, but the clothing costs are much higher for
the adults. So if you were to just take all the clothing
costs from the estate for all of the heirs, it would not
be fair to the young. heirs,
because the older guys are the ones, they have higher costs, let
that come from their portion of the estate. Don't let it come
from the estate equally, and the reverse by the case of the
food costs. So that's what the משנה mishna says. המניח בנים גדולים
וקטנים, Hamaniach banim gedolim u'ketanim, אין הגדולים מתפרנסים. ein hagedolim mitparnasim. So
the word מתפרנס mitparnes refers specifically here to clothing costs. So the
elders cannot, the older kids cannot have the estate pay for their
clothing costs על ידי הקטנים al yedei haketanim by having like, oh,
the estate will just pay for all of our clothing costs. No.
They're taking advantage of the younger kids whose clothing costs are not
as great. The younger kids don't need like Armani suits. Okay? ולא
הקטנים ניזונים על הגדולים. Velo haketanim nizonim al hagedolim. And the younger
kids cannot say let's just have the food costs come off of
the top of the estate because then their costs are higher than
the older kids and that's not fair to them. So they can't
do it at the expense of the older kids.
אלא חולקים בשווה, Ella cholkim beshava, you divide the estate equally and
then it comes from everybody's individual portion.
All right? נשאו גדולים ישאו קטנים. Nasu gedolim yisu ketanim. Now if
the older kids got
married and that money was used in that case
from, money was used from the estate to make for the wedding
costs, okay, and that was after the father had died, so money
went from the estate for the wedding costs. So when it comes
time for the younger kids to get married, they can take that
money from the entire estate. They don't have to take it specifically
from their portion and they take, you know, the same amount of
wedding costs. Fair is fair. נשאו גדולים ישאו קטנים ואם אמרו קטנים
הרי אנו נושאים כדרך שנשאתם אתם, Nasu gedolim yisu ketanim ve'im amru
ketanim harei anu nosim kederach shenasatem atem, but if the young kids
say we're going to get married just like you got married, אינם
שומעין להם, einam shomin lahem, you don't listen to them. Now that
on the face of it doesn't make sense. We just said the
line just before this said that if you spent money on the
wedding costs for the elder kids, you spend it for the younger
kids and here it says the younger kids can't say it. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to explain that what this means is
that the younger kids, if the older kids got married when the
father was still alive and money didn't come from the estate, so
money came from the father's property and then the father died and
now it's time for the younger kids to get married, they can't
say, oh, well let's, you know, let's just take that money from
the estate in general.
No. Sorry. The timing I understand didn't work out and appreciate that,
but when the older kids got their wedding costs paid, they were
paid by the father and it's seen as a gift from the
father. Now the father is dead, now this estate is owned equally,
you can't demand that your wedding gets paid from the estate from
your older brother's portion. You have to have those costs paid from
specifically your portion. Okay? So either the estate is paying equally for
everyone, but if the money came specifically before it became an estate,
then it's on each individual to take care of their own costs.
ואם אמרו קטנים הרי אנו נושאים כדרך שנשאתם אתם אינם שומעין להם,
Ve'im amru ketanim harei
anu nosim kederach shenasatem atem ein shomin lahem, אלא מה שנתן להם
אביהם נתן. ella mah shenatan lahem avihem natan.
What the father gave the older kids he gave and that's irrelevant
now. That's ancient history and now the estate gets divided equally.
Okay. המניח בנות גדולות וקטנות. Hamaniach banot gedolot u'ketanot. Now we're going
to say the same thing except with girls.
If the father died and left a lot of girls and no
sons and they all inherit the estate and there were older girls
and younger girls, daughters I should say, המניח בנות גדולות וקטנות, hamaniach
banot gedolot u'ketanot, וקטנות, u'ketanot, אין הגדולות מתפרנסות על ידי הקטנות ולא
הקטנות ניזונות על הגדולות אלא חולקות בשווה. ein hagedolot mitparnasot al yedei
haketanot velo haketanot nizonot al hagedolot ella cholkot beshava.
Exactly the same הלכה. halacha. You know you can't go ahead and
equally take and just have everybody's clothing costs get paid from the
estate because then that's the older,
the women, the daughters who are older, their clothing costs are higher.
That's not fair. They're taking
advantage to take it equally from the estate. It's taking advantage of
the younger daughters and the reverse by the food costs. Okay? So
you have to divide the estate and everybody has to pay their
costs from their portion. אלא חולקות בשווה. Ella cholkot beshava. נשאו גדולות
ישאו קטנות. Nasu gedolot yisu ketanot. Same הלכה. halacha.
If after the father died the older daughters got married and take
money off of the estate, then when it's time for the younger
daughters to get married, you take money from the entire estate. ואם
אמרו קטנות הרי
אנו נושאות כדרך שנשאתם אתן. Ve'im amru ketanot harei anu nosot kederach
shenasatem aten. But if the older daughters got married when the father
was alive and he paid for the costs or gave a dowry
or whatever and now the younger daughters say we're going to get
married just like you did and we're going to take it from
the estate, אין שומעין להן, ein shomin lahen, you don't listen to
them. Okay. Exact same הלכות. halachas. So then why did it repeat
it? Because of the last line. זה חומר בבנים מבבנות. Ze chomer
bebanim mibebanot.
Here's one way in which the case by the daughters is different
than the case by the sons. שהבנות ניזונות על הבנים ואין ניזונות
על הבנות. shehabanot nizonot al habanim ve'ein nizonot al habanot. That if
you have a case, which we'll see really in the next פרק,
perek, you have a case where
there are sons and daughters and the sons inherit then the daughters
have a right. right to be supported from the estate. Okay, that's
a special תנאי כתובה tenai ksuva that basically the father, the husband
writes to the wife when he writes the כתובה, ksuva, that if
I die, you know, you as my wife will have a right
to your sort of costs, food and upkeep etc. will be paid
from the estate until you get remarried or take your lump sum
כתובה. ksuva. And the daughters, you know, they also will be able
to be
supported—food, lodging, etc.—from the money of the estate until they get remarried.
So, therefore, in a case of when it's sons and daughters, the
sons inherit the estate, then the daughters are supported by it. Whereas
if it's daughters and daughters, right, so it's not like some daughters
are supported off of the estate that other daughters have, they all
equally inherit. So that's saying that that's a greater stringency because this
idea that, you know, for the younger kids, the cost of food
is more expensive. So if it's young girls and boys, then the
girls say, well, you gotta pay high food costs, that's coming from
the estate. But if it's girls and girls, then it's like, no,
the young girls can't say our food costs are coming from the
estate, that's where they have to divide it equally. Okay, let's see
the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבא האי גדול אחי דלבש ואיכסי מביסה
מאי דעבד עבד. Amar Rava hai gadol achi delavash ve-ichasi mibeisa mai
de-avid avid. If actually the oldest son who represents the household, he's
the one, you know, that might go into the court and do
business for the estate and represents the family, he, if he's using
money from the estate for his clothes, so that's acceptable. Okay, meaning
even though the משנה Mishnah seems to teach no, everybody's gotta pay
their own clothing costs, what he is saying is the remaining oldest
heir who represents the estate and represents the interests of the family,
his clothing costs are really for the benefit of the entire estate
and that can come off of the entire estate, not out of
his personal share. Although the language רבא Rava used is מאי דעבד
עבד, mai de-avid avid, that if he did it, it's okay. Ideally,
maybe that should come from his private share because as you could
imagine, you know, that could be really subject to abuse. Well, you
know, I need ten Armani suits and I need a Porsche and
I need all these things in order, you know, to look good
and it's all for the sake of the family. So because of
that, it's—because of that, I would say a potential for misuse, it's
בדיעבד, bedieved, it's okay and maybe even there בית דין Beis Din
can intervene and assess, okay, but there it actually is for the
benefit of everyone and it does come from the entire estate. So
the גמרא Gemara says, ואנן תנן אין הגדולים מתפרנסים על הקטנים? V'anan
tenan ein hagedolim mitparnesim al haktanim? But one minute, our משנה Mishnah
says that the older sons cannot have their food costs paid from
the entire estate—excuse me, their clothing costs paid from the entire estate?
So the גמרא Gemara says, מתניתין בסרחא. Masnisin besircha.
So our משנה Mishnah is talking about like a lounge-about, okay, somebody
that is a—yeah, they're older sons, but they're not, you know, they're
not actually representing the interests of the family. So the גמרא Gemara
says, סרחא פשיטא! Sircha peshita! Now, isn't that obvious? Of course then
they can't; there wouldn't even be a reason to think that their
higher clothing costs could be paid from the general estate. מהו דתימא
ניחא להו דלא ניזיל, Mah de-teima nichu lehu delo nizil, maybe even
in those cases, it's to the benefit of the entire family that
the older sons don't, you know, dress nicely even if they're just
lounging about, you know, it's still good for their status, קא משמע
לן kamashma lan that it's not; it's not in the interest of
the family. Only if it's somebody that really is representing the estate.
It is interesting that the גמרא Gemara made it sound like the
משנה Mishnah was the exception, whereas really it should—you know, it sounds
more that רבא's Rava the exception. A normal case of older sons
and whatever, fine, you know, you can't take that money for your
clothes out of the estate. If you have such a case where
somebody represents the family and is doing it in order because he's
out there in public representing the family, that's רבא's Rava special case.
It's funny the way the גמרא's Gemara almost turned it into the
fact like the משנה Mishnah was the special case. All right, let's
keep on going. נשאו גדולים ישאו קטנים. Nasu gedolim yisu ktanim. So,
you know, if the older ones got married from money from the
estate, they use money for the wedding costs, so the younger ones
can do the same. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי קאמר? Mai
kama? How does the first line
fit with the next line? The next line says, oh, but, you
know, the younger ones can't say we want to get married just
like you guys got married, because the shift in context isn't clear
in the משנה. Mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי קאמר אמר
רב יהודה הכי קאמר. Mai kama? Amar Rav Yehuda hachi kama. This
is what it's saying. נשאו גדולים אחר מיתת אביהם, Nasu gedolim achar
misas avihem, if the older sons got married after the father died
and they took money for the wedding costs from the top of
the estate, ישאו קטנים אחר מיתת אביהם, yisu ktanim achar misas avihem,
the younger sons can do the same; they're entitled to take the
same amount of money from the estate. אבל נשאו גדולים בחיי אביהם,
Aval nasu gedolim bechayei avihem,
that's the critical line of context that was not spelled out in
the משנה, Mishnah, but if the older sons got married when the
father was alive, then that money wasn't coming from the estate, that
money was a gift from the father. אבל נשאו גדולים בחיי אביהם
ואמרו קטנים אחר מיתת אביהם, Aval nasu gedolim bechayei avihem v'amru ktanim
achar misas avihem, and then the younger sons said after the father
died, let's take an equal amount from the estate of the amount
that dad paid. for your wedding when he was alive, okay, אבל
לאחר מיתת אביהם הרי אנו נושאים כדרך שנשאתם
Aval l'achar mitat avihem
harei anu nosim k'derech shenisatem אין שומעין להם ein shomin lahem אלא
מה שנתן להם אביהם נתן. ela mah shenatan lahem avihem natan. What
the father gave
the older sons, that was a gift from the father. And now,
we're not dealing with the father anymore, we're dealing with the estate,
and you don't have a right to take it from the estate.
Okay, הניח בנות גדולות וקטנות. Hiniach banot gedolot u'ktanot. Now we get
to the second part which is a case of daughters. Again, it's
really the exact same הלכה. halacha. It was really only said because
of the last line of the idea which is going to be
the beginning of the next פרק, perek, which is about how daughters
get supported by the estate that the sons inherit. So let's see
though what the גמרא Gemara has to say about this. שלח ליה
אבוה בר גניבא
לרבא. Shelach lei Avuha
bar Geniva l'Rava. So אבוה בר גניבא Avuha bar Geniva sent to
רבא: Rava: ילמדנו רבנו, Yilmadenu rabenu, let our master teach us. לותה
ואכלה ועמדה וניסת, Lavta v'achla v'amda v'nisat, בעל לוקח הוי או יורש
הוי?
ba'al lokeach havei o
yoresh havei?
If a woman borrowed money, so she you know, she whatever, she
went to some loaners and she now has ten thousand dollars of
debt, and then she goes ahead and she gets married and she
brings property into the marriage, maybe that her father gave her, and
the husband has rights to this property. This is נכסי מלוג. nichsei
milog. He doesn't have title, the woman has the title, but the
husband has usufruct, the right to the פירות perot of this property.
Okay, now remember if this was her own private property, let's assume
she borrowed the money once she already had this property, so the
loaners, so the creditors had liens on this property. And now those
creditors, now that she's married, okay, she brought this property into the
marriage, but now they want to get their debt paid up and
they want to exercise those liens and they want to take the
property. So what is the status of the husband vis-a-vis these נכסי
מלוג? nichsei milog? Okay, that's the question. בעל לוקח הוי או יורש
הוי? Ba'al lokeach havei o yoresh havei? Is he like he purchased
this property from his wife or is he like he inherits it?
Now, it's really a little bit funny because you would say that
that's a reasonable question to ask after the wife died. You know,
after the wife dies, so a husband inherits from his wife, but
here's property that he already had a right to and then he
fully inherits after she dies, and you could ask what's his relationship
to it, you know, now that he inherited it. Do we treat
him as a just as a normal heir or do we say
since he had a right when she was still alive, then even
after she died, he's sort of like a purchaser and less like
an heir? What's the relevance? The relevance is this case, okay, because
there are cases here of a creditor. A creditor has liens, but
if there's no שטר, shtar, then a creditor cannot exercise those liens
in the absence of a שטר shtar from somebody who purchased the
property. You have to protect innocent purchasers, and without a שטר, shtar,
and nobody knows that those liens exist, those liens can't be exercised.
But the liens can be exercised even without a שטר shtar against
the heirs. So you know, יעקב Yaakov dies and then ראובן Reuven
inherits from him, so even if it was a מלווה על פה,
milveh al peh, even if there's no שטר, shtar, the creditors can
collect from ראובן. Reuven. Okay, because you don't have to protect ראובן.
Reuven. ראובן Reuven didn't purchase the property, he just inherited it. So
therefore the creditor, we he has right to his money back, he
can collect, he can exercise his liens against ראובן. Reuven. Okay, so
that's the question being asked here in the case of the wife.
Can the creditor now exercise those liens and collect the property? But
again, it's a question that makes more sense after she's dead and
then you could say do we look at the husband as as
an inheritor or do we look at him as a type of
a purchaser? Are we going to try to protect his interests or
not protect his interests? Okay, while the wife is still alive, it
makes a little less sense, but let's see because then he doesn't
even have title yet to the land. But let's see what the
גמרא Gemara does with it, okay? So let's take a look. ועמדה
וניסת בעל לוקח הוי או יורש הוי? V'amda v'nisat ba'al lokeach havei
o yoresh havei? לוקח הוי, Lokeach havei, do we look at the
husband's, you know, relationship to this property that his wife brought in
as if he purchased the property? ומלווה על פה, U'milveh al peh,
and because now this is a debt that, you know, there are
creditors but it's money but there's no שטר, shtar, it's only all
just an oral transaction, so אינו גובה מן הלקוחות, eino goveh min
halakochot, so the creditors do not have rights to exercise their liens
against people that purchased the property if there's no שטר, shtar, so
they can't exercise their liens against the husband and collect, you know,
the property from the debt of the from the debt of the
wife. או דילמא יורש הוי? O dilma yoresh havei?
Or maybe we look at the husband vis-a-vis his wife's property as
if he inherited this property, you know, he didn't pay for it
or anything of that nature. או דילמא יורש הוי ומלווה על פה
גובה מן היורשים? O dilma yoresh havei u'milveh al peh goveh min
hayorshim? And therefore the wife's creditors can collect the same way even
without a שטר shtar you can collect from heirs. So therefore the
wife's creditors can collect her debt from the husband. That's the question.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so that was the question that was posed
to רבא. Rava. So רבא Rava said back, תנינא, Tenina, and that's
basically taught in our משנה. Mishna. You were wondering why we were
asking this question? It's because it's connected to our משנה. Mishna. He
says it's taught in our משנה. Mishna. הניח בנות גדולות וקטנות. Hiniach
banot gedolot u'ktanot.
So If the older daughters got married, the younger daughters can get
married from the money of the estate. Now, remember, what does that
mean the money of the estate? Well, it's the money they all
inherited. So he's going to assume the older daughters got married,
let's call them Sarah and Rivka got married. Assume Sarah, Rivka, Rachel,
and Leah are all daughters. Sarah and Rivka got married, and their
wedding cost $20,000, and then they brought now also their share of
the estate
into their marriages. That's their property that they brought into their marriages,
their share of the estate. Now the younger daughters, Rachel and Leah,
it's their time to get married, and they want $20,000 for their
wedding, and they want that to come equally from the estate, so
meaning some of it is going to come from the portions of
Sarah and Rivka. So they are going to now get part of
their wedding paid from
the money of the estate that Sarah and Rivka brought into their
marriages. So that's exactly our case. They had a right, they had
a debt as it were against the estate, money that they were
owed for when it became their time to marry.
Sarah and Rivka went ahead with this debt against the property, took
this property into their marriage with their husbands, and now they are
going to get that loan paid off from that property that is
in the hands of the husbands of Sarah and Rivka. So that
was pretty ingenious. Okay, so let's take a look. תנינא *tanina*, we
taught in our משנה Mishnah, *mishnah*: נישאת גדולה ישיא קטנה *nisat gedola
yasia katana*. מאי לאו *mai lav*, are we not talking that נישאת
גדולה לבעל *nisat gedola l'baal*, that the older ones married a husband,
so Sarah and Rivka got married, ישיא קטנה *yasia katana* now when
it comes time for Rachel and Leah to get married, מבעל *mibaal*,
they can get their portion that they have a right to from
the estate for their wedding costs to come from the husbands,
from the property that Sarah and Rivka brought into their marriage? All
right, so that seems to be yes, and therefore it's like a
יורש yoresh, *yoresh*, and they do have a right to exercise their
lien. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says not necessarily, לא *lo*, נישאת
גדולה לבעל ישיא קטנה לבעל *nisat gedola l'baal yasia katana l'baal*. No,
maybe what
actually is not talking about such a complicated case. It's not talking
about the case that the estate was divided and Sarah and Rivka
brought it in and now we're going to take it away from
Sarah and Rivka, that portion of their estate that they brought into
their marriage. Who says we're talking about such a complicated case? Maybe
what it means is Sarah and Rivka got married, they didn't bring
any money, or they didn't bring the money of the estate in
because the estate had not been divided yet, the estate is still
sitting there, Sarah and Rivka's husbands do not have any rights to
the estate, and it's from that money that you pay for the
wedding for Rachel and Leah, and it has nothing to do with
our case. So maybe that is what is going on.
So we do not know an answer, but that's why we're learning
it. We learned it because of its connection to the משנה Mishnah.
*mishnah*, and now we're going to keep on going until we can
see if we can come to a conclusion.
Let's take a look. ישיא קטנה מבעל איני *yasia katana mibaal eini*,
is that really true, this possibility that the husband is a לוקח
lokeach. *lokeach* and not a יורש yoresh. *yoresh*? Is it really true
that you might not have a right to exercise your lien? והתני
רבי חייא *v'tani Rabbi Hiyya*, or this reading of the משנה Mishnah:
*mishnah*, excuse me, that the money is coming from the undivided estate
and the משנה Mishna *mishnah* does not mean that the money is
coming from the property that was already divided. והתני רבי חייא *v'tani
Rabbi Hiyya*, but רבי חייא *Rabbi Hiyya* teaches in a ברייתא *beraita*:
נישאת גדולה לבעל ישיא קטנה מבעל *nisat gedola l'baal yasia katana mibaal*.
So רבי חייא *Rabbi Hiyya* teaches explicitly the way you wanted to
read it, that when the younger daughters have a right to now
get their wedding paid for from the estate, it means even that
when the estate was divided and now is in the property
of the marriage of the older daughters. So you see that they
can exercise their lien and the husband is like a יורש yoresh,
*yoresh*. That answers our question. So that seems pretty conclusive. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. No, דילמא שאני פרנסה דאית
לה קלא *dilma shani parnasa d'it lah kala*, maybe that's true in
that case about the wedding, but פרנסה *parnasa*, but פרנסה *parnasa* is
a generic term of
different types of support that isn't מזונות *mezonot*. Before we were using
it to refer to clothing, here we're using it to refer to
the costs of the wedding. What the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying
is maybe the general rule is that a creditor cannot exercise his
lien against the husband, a property that the wife brings into the
estate. But in our case it's different because in our case the
idea, because it's always a question of whose interests are you trying
to protect,
and maybe the husband doesn't realize that there are these liens and
you gotta protect the husband's interest, he's marrying this woman with the
expectation he's bringing in this property and so on. But in this
case, the same husband who got married from the money of the
estate. He is, it's known that oh I married שרה or רבקה
Rivka and it cost twenty thousand dollars, she should figure out that
רחל Rachel and לאה Leah also also have a twenty thousand dollar
lien on the estate and therefore that is well known their right
to that and therefore in that case we allow them to exercise
their liens but we would not as a general rule allow somebody
to exercise the liens against the husband.
Okay, so we can't prove it from the case of the wedding
because the wedding might be an exception that we
say basically to the husband you should have known that your wife
had those liens on the estate and we're not going to let
the younger daughters exercise their liens but it would not necessarily be
true in general in a case of a creditor against the property
the wife brings into her marriage. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא:
Amar lei Rav Pappa le-Rava: רב פפא Rav Pappa said to רבא,
Rava, לאו היינו דשלח רבין באגרתיה? Lav hainu de-shalach Ravin be-igratei? Wait
a minute, isn't the answer to this question about יורש או לוקח
Yoresh o Lokeach and whether a creditor can exercise liens basically what
רבין Ravin sent in a letter? What did רבין Ravin sent in
a letter? מי שמת והניח אלמנה ובת. Mi she-met ve-hinniach almana u-vat.
Somebody died and no sons and left over a wife and a
daughter. Now you'll remember that the אלמנה, almana, the widow, has the
right to be supported from the estate until she gets remarried or
collects her
כתובה, ketubah, her lump sum כתובה, ketubah, and now she's collecting the
estate that is in the possession of the daughter. Okay, so let's
take a look.
אלמנתו ניזונת מנכסיו. Almanato nizonet mi-nechasav. So the אלמנה, almana, the widow,
gets supported from the estate that's now in the possession of the
daughter. נישאת הבת, אלמנתו ניזונת מנכסיו. Nisset ha-bat, almanato nizonet mi-nechasav. Now
the daughter gets married, she still gets continued to get supported from
the estate. So right there, that seems to be an exact perfect
example. She gets supported from the estate. This is she had a
she was a creditor, she had a lien against the estate for
her support. The daughter took this property, brought it into her marriage,
and she continues to get payment from that estate. So that seems
to be an exact perfect example. And again, יורש, yoresh the creditor
does have rights. Okay,
מתה הבת. Meta ha-bat. Now let's say it's the case where the
daughter actually dies and now it's transferred to her husband. That is
really where you need to ask יורש או לוקח. yoresh o lokeach.
Because as I was saying before, before the daughter died, the husband
doesn't even really own the property yet. So it's actually somewhat of
a funny question and תוספות Tosafot deals with that. But now the
daughter died and transferred to the husband. Now we really want to
know, will the wife still be able to get continued to be
supported? Will the husband be considered like a יורש או לוקח? yoresh
o lokeach? And let's see what the הלכה halakhah is. מתה הבת,
אמר רב יהודה בן אחותו של רבי יוסי בר חנינא: Meta ha-bat,
amar Rav Yehuda ben achoto shel Rabbi Yossi bar Chanina: לדידי הוה
עובדא. Le-didi hava uvda. This case happened to me. ואמרו, Ve-amru, and
the ruling came down: אלמנתו ניזונת מנכסיו. Almanato nizonet mi-nechasav. Yes, the
widow still gets supported even after the husband even after the wife
dies and the husband gets it. The liens can still be exercised.
So the husband is basically treated as a יורש. yoresh, All right,
that seems to be a pretty good example and that's similar to
what רבא Rava wanted to prove from our משנה, Mishna. that the
liens can still be exercised. אלא, Ela, so one minute... ואמרו ניזונת
מנכסיו. Ve-amru nizonet mi-nechasav. אי אמרת בשלמא יורש הוי. Ei amrat bishlama
yoresh havei. So if the husband is considered a יורש, yoresh. so
היינו דאלמנתו ניזונת מנכסיו. hainu de-almanato nizonet mi-nechasav.
That's why the widow can still exercise the liens, because it's considered
she still has rights, just like a creditor can exercise liens even
after the heirs inherit, even though there's no שטר. shtar. אלא אי
אמרת לוקח הוי. Ela ei amrat lokeach havei. But if the husband
is a purchaser, אמאי ניזונת מנכסיו? amai nizonet mi-nechasav? Why can the
widow be supported? Right, this is just like a מלוה על פה.
milveh al peh. So you see that he is a יורש yoresh,
and the liens can still be exercised. That seems to be a
pretty good proof. אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. So that was support of
רבא. Rava. Comes in אביי, Abaye, and אביי Abaye says: אי לאו
דשלח רבין אנן לא ידעינן? Ei lav de-shalach Ravin anan lo yad’inan?
Oh, you're telling me it's all implicit in what רבין Ravin said.
אביי Abaye says this whole thing is even more obvious. I would
have known that idea already from a משנה. Mishna והתנן, Ve-ha-tenan, and
we taught in the משנה: Mishna אלו הן שאין חוזרין ביובל. Elu
hen she-ein chozrin be-yovel. The following things do not return to their
original owners in the יובל: yovel: הבכורה. Ha-bechorah. The extra portion of
the בכורה. bechorah. That's not considered like a purchase. Only purchases return
in the יובל. yovel. So a ירושה yerushah doesn't return, and a
בכורה bechorah even though it's called like a מתנה, matanah, so it's
not a purchase. But on the other hand it's not a ירושה
yerushah but because it's not a purchase, okay, so that doesn't isn't
חוזר, chozer, isn't חוזר ביובל. chozer be-yovel.
So number one. And turning the page, קל"ט עמוד ב'. Kuf Lamed
Tet Amud Bet. והיורש את אשתו. Ve-ha-yoresh et ishto. A husband who
inherits his wife. So you see that when the wife dies and
the husband gets it, he's considered a יורש, yoresh. not a לוקח.
lokeiach. So all of these things support the idea that he is
a יורש. yoresh. Great, so that should end our story, we'll all
go to bed. But let's take a look. אמר ליה רב... Amar
lei Rav... And turning the page, קל"ט עמוד ב', Kof Lamed Tet
Amud Bet, והיורש את אשתו, Veha-yoresh et ishto, a husband who inherits
his wife. So you see that when the wife dies and the
husband gets it, he's considered a יורש, yoresh, not a לוקח. lokeiach
So all of these things support the idea that he's a יורש.
yoresh. Great. So that should end our story. We'll all go to
bed. But let's take a look. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava,
so now we have all these things that supported רבא Rava from
our משנה Mishna about when the girls have to pay for their
wedding, the thing that רבין Rabin sent about when the widow gets
supported from the estate even after the daughter remarries and even after
the daughter dies and the husband inherits. And this הלכה halacha that
it's not חוזר ביובל. chozer b'Yovel. All of these things indicate that
the husband is a יורש. yoresh, Comes back רבא Rava and רבא
Rava now is going to make trouble. So אמר ליה רבא, Amar
lei Rava, so רבא Rava said back to אביי, Abaye, והשתא דשלח
מדינא, Vehashata d'shlach Midina, now look, just because you said, oh who
even needs רבין, Rabin, we know it from the משנה. רבא Rava
now says, even with what רבין Rabin says, are we so sure
that we really know the answer to this question? והאמר רבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא, Veha-amar Rabbi Yossi berabi Chanina, didn't רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא
Rabbi Yossi berabi Chanina say, באושא התקינו האישה שמכרה בנכסי מלוג בחיי
בעלה ומתה הבעל מוציא מיד הלקוחות? Be-Usha hitkinu ha-isha she-machra be-nichsei milog
be-chayei ba'ala u-meta ha-ba'al motzi mi-yad ha-lakochot?
If a woman sells this property, נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog, that she
has title to and the husband has rights of פירות, peirot, and
she sells it while her husband is alive and she has title,
okay, now if the husband were to die and then she would
get back the right of פירות, peirot, then the fact that she
sold it to this guy, it would transfer to this guy. Okay,
but that's not what happened. What happened is that it's not that
the husband died first, she died first. So now what's the story?
She died first
and she sold her title to this guy. Does the husband get
to stake his claim and say she died, it's coming to me,
or is it like, no, sorry, now this other person now already
owns the title, so you only would have inherited if it had
been in her possession when she died, but she already sold the
title to this other guy? So what's the הלכה? halacha? So in
אושא Usha they established, הבעל מוציא מיד הלקוחות, ha-ba'al motzi mi-yad ha-lakochot,
that the husband can go say to this guy, this ראובן Reuven
or whoever it is, I'm sorry buddy, I'm taking possession of it.
Now why does he have a right to do that? Because if
he's a יורש, yoresh,
so if somebody's father sells something and then the father dies, the
son doesn't get to say, oh give it back to me. You
only get what was left in the father's hands. So you, the
husband, should only get what the wife had left in her hands,
and you wouldn't have a right to go and claim it from
this other guy if your relationship to the property when she died
would be a יורש. But if you're considered to be a לוקח
lokeiach. as your relationship to the property when you were married and
then that ownership gets strengthened, then basically now you can go to
this ראובן Reuven and say, hey ראובן, Reuven, you bought it from
my wife, but I actually had bought it from my wife first.
Okay,
so that seems to be that we understand, again, there's a whole
mix-up here between are we talking about his relationship when the wife
is still alive or after she died. Again, תוספות Tosafot discusses it.
We're going to just sort of not try to fully unpack that.
Okay, but basically if the husband's rights to the property was that
of an heir, then once the wife sold it, it's out of
the, then
he no longer has rights. The fact that even after the wife
sold it, if the wife dies he can go ahead and demand
his claim shows that his relationship is that of a לוקח. lokeiach.
So now we've got a problem. We have all this evidence that
shows יורש, but this תקנה takana of אושא Usha that shows לוקח.
lokeiach. Okay, now the fact that it required a תקנה takana might
show that that's not the עיקר הדין ikar ha-din and maybe every
case has a different הלכה, halacha, which is exactly sort of where
the גמרא Gemara is getting towards. So let's see what the גמרא
says. אלא אמר רב אשי, Ela amar Rav Ashi, says רב אשי,
Rav Ashi, בעל שוויוה רבנן כיורש ושוויוה רבנן כלוקח. Ba'al shaviyuh rabanan
ke-yoresh u-shaviyuh rabanan ke-lokeiach. Don't look for one answer. Okay, there are
different cases. Sometimes they made him like a יורש, sometimes like a
לוקח. lokeiach What was the guiding principle? So he says, והיכא דטבא
ליה עבדו ליה, ve-heicha d'tava lei avdu lei, where it was for
his benefit, that's what they did. Now not always his benefit, but
basically we're trying to focus on his benefit, but we're trying to
also make sure that people don't suffer undue losses. So let's go
through the cases. Okay, so גבי יובל, gabei Yovel, when it comes
to יובל, Yovel, שוויוה רבנן כיורש משום פסידא דידיה, shaviyuh rabanan ke-yoresh
mishum pesida didey, right, his wife dies, he inherits, now there's a
יובל, Yovel, the property is going to go back, I mean, that's
going to uproot sort of the whole normal expectation, right, and it's
his, property he got from his marriage and so on, so we're
not going to do that. That's going to be highly disruptive and
seem unfair to him. Okay, so משום פסידא דידיה. mishum pesida didey.
גבי דרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Gabei de-Rabbi Yossi berabi Chanina, regarding the
case of רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yossi berabi Chanina about אושא,
Usha, so in that case שוויוה רבנן כלוקח משום פסידא דידיה.
shaviyuh rabanan ke-lokeiach mishum pesida didey.
That certainly works in his interest. Both of these things are in
his interest. He doesn't have to lose the property at the יובל,
Yovel, and if his wife sold the property, then he gets to
say, no sorry, I'm reclaiming it if she died before
him, because we want to protect his interest, so we're going to
make him like a לוקח and that he can reclaim that property.
גבי דרבין, Gabei de-Rabin, the case of רבין Rabin about the widow
being supported from the estate, okay, when again, the daughter and then
the daughter gets married and then she dies and the widow still
gets
supported, so that... Because of it would be unfair to the widow
that she would no longer be able to get supported. So again
in the case where the wife dies and he inherits we don't
want him to lose it in the יובל *Yovel* so we say
he's a יורש *yoresh*. When the wife sells it we don't want
him to lose his rights so we say he's a לוקח *lokeach*
if she dies and he can claim his rights. When the wife
dies and now the money has to be used to pay the
wife's mother who is a אלמנה *almanah*, okay, so there even though
she has a right to it, she's a creditor, so we're going
to consider so even though obviously he's going to lose it's only
fair she's going to continue to be able to be supported, we're
going to make him into a יורש *yoresh*. גבי דרבין משום פסידת
אלמנה שוויוהו רבנן כיורש *Gabbai deRavin mishum pesidat almanah shavinu rabanan k'yoresh*.
Okay. Now what we haven't answered was the case we started with,
which was a normal case about a woman taking out loans getting
married, can the creditors exercise their liens. And the רשב"ם *Rashbam* said
yes, you see that from the case of the אלמנה *almanah* that
basically we want there to be a certain fairness here, okay, so
if somebody is owed money, whether it be the אלמנה *almanah*, whether
it be the creditors, they have a right to exercise their liens
against this property that the woman brought into her marriage and that
the husband now owns. All right, so that's the הלכה *halacha* and
that also by he's also a יורש *yoresh* for the הלכה *halacha*
of יובל *Yovel* so he doesn't have to lose his thing and
the only thing that sort of doesn't fit with the יורש *yoresh*
example is this case of אושא *Usha* where again that's a special
thing we're doing to protect his interests that the wife doesn't get
to sort of sell it out from under him. But now the
גמרא *Gemara* is going to say but wait one minute, there's other
people who are losing out by that תקנה *takana* of אושא *Usha*.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says והא גבי דרבי יוסי בר חנינא דאיכא
פסידה ללקוחות שוויוהו רבנן כלוקח *ve'ha gabbi de'Rabbi Yose bar Chanina d'ika
pesida lilukochos shavinu rabanan kelokeach*. In the case of אושא *Usha* where
the wife sold it out from under him, if you want to
protect the creditors and you want to protect the אלמנה *almanah*, why
aren't you concerned about the people that this ראובן *Reuven* that bought
the property from the wife, husband's now going to come take it
and seize it and take it back. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
no, that's different. התם אינהו אפסידו אנפשייהו *hatam inu afsidu anafshaihu*. They
knew the risk that they were taking. Okay. כיון דאיכא בעל לא
איבעי ליה למיזבן מאיתתא דאיסתויא גברא *keivan d'ika ba'al lo iba'i lei
limizban mi'itata d'isatusei gavra*. They knew that she was married. They knew
that the rule was that if she died the husband would inherit.
So when they were buying it, I mean it all of course
depends how well known is the law, but anyway when they were
buying it they knew that they were buying this property, it was
a risk, who is going to die first the husband or the
wife, and they certainly hopefully did not pay full price. So in
that case it's their risk, buyer beware, they assumed the risk. Okay.
And therefore we're going to more protect the husband's case. But in
a normal case of a creditor, a normal case of an אלמנה
*almanah*, so those people are owed money and they're going to have
a right to exercise their liens. Bottom line is it basically is
יורש *yoresh* and the creditor and the אלמנה *almanah* have a right
to exercise their liens and the real exception is this case of
the תקנה *takana* of אושא *Usha*. Okay. Now we are going to
do the הדרן עלך יש נוחלין *hadran alach yesh nochalin*. Finally done
with that very large פרק *perek*. Let's give a start to the
next פרק *perek* here and this is again going to be the
principle about daughters getting supported from the estate. מי שמת והניח בנים
ובנות *mi shemeit vehiniach banim uvanot*. Somebody died and left behind sons
and daughters. בזמן שהנכסים מרובים הבנים יירשו והבנות ייזונו *bizman she'nechasim merubim
habanim yirshu vehabanot yizonu*. When there is a lot of property, and
the גמרא *Gemara* will basically describe that a lot of property here
means that enough of the estate is worth enough to support the
daughters until they reach the age of maturity of בגרות *bagrut*, they're
supported until they, I think I said before earlier in this שיעור
*shiur* that until they get married that's true but it's also until
they reach reach the age of
maturity, okay, so they get supported until they reach the age of
maturity. If there is not enough money or just enough money for
that then basically the money of the estate is considered to be
under the control of the daughters. They claim to it and they
have a right to ensure
that what's owed them, that
their support until they reach the age of maturity, that that is
going to be under their possession, that's their claim to the estate.
That's considered נכסים מועטים nechasim muatim *nechasim muatim* that there's just enough
money to ensure
or not enough, but not more than the money to ensure that
the daughters are
supported in terms of their costs of upkeep. Okay. If there however
is more than that amount then the money is all the estate
is considered under the control of the sons and the daughters have
a claim to it for their support. So if it's up to
or less than the amount
needed for their support, that's called נכסים מועטים nechasim muatim, *nechasim muatim*
and then it's fundamentally under the control of the daughters. If it's
more than that amount then it's under the control of the sons,
they're going to actually be left with some inheritance and the daughters
have a lien on the estate. So let's read that. בזמן שנכסים
מרובים if there's a lot of property, enough beyond just the support
for the daughters, הבנים יירשו והבנות יזונו Habanim yirshu vehabanot yizonu then
the sons inherit and they're seen to take possession of the entire
estate, and the daughters are now fed off of it, they have
a claim to be fed off of the estate but it's under
basically the control of the sons. נכסים מועטים nechasim muatim? if it
is a small amount of property, meaning equal or less than the
amount needed to support the daughters. So in that case, הבנות יזונו
Habanot yizonu you start with the fact that the daughters are supported,
meaning that the property is
basically portioned off and given under their control. הבנות יזונו Habanot yizonu
and
the sons have to go ahead and they have to go begging,
meaning so besides what I've been focusing on as under whose control
it is, it's also that sons are left with nothing. So
אדמון Admon says what, just because I'm a male aren't males supposed
to have it better here in Judaism? So that means that I
don't get support from any support from the estate? Okay, so there's
a question whether he's actually claiming that in such a case the
sons and daughters should be supported equally
for their upkeep or is he just sort of expressing outrage. אמר
רבן גמליאל רואה אני את דברי אדמון Amar Rabban Gamliel ro'eh ani
et divrei Admon and Rabban Gamliel says I see Admon's point. So
there's an interesting question
again whether that's an actual different halakhic position or not. The general
assumption either way is that we don't rule that way. That that
is the halakhah that if the girls, if there's only enough money
to support the girls, then the boys basically have to go hungry,
have to go begging. Okay, so וכמה מרובים vechama merubim how much
is a lot? I've already given the basic parameters, but let's see
what the Gemara says. וכמה מרובים. Vechama merubim. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב כדי שיזונו מהן אלו ואלו שנים עשר חודש Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav kedei sheyizonu mehen elu va'elu shenayim asar chodesh enough to
support the boys and the girls for twelve months. Interesting that he
mentions the boys. The real focus is the girls. We'll get to
that in a minute, but basically even if the girls are going
to be many years until they reach the age of maturity, nevertheless
once there's enough for everybody for a year, more than enough for
everybody for a year, the estate is under the control of the
boys. The part of the question really here is under whose control
it is. The girls still have the claim to be supported until
they reach maturity, but once there's enough for everybody for a year,
then the estate is under their control. That's what he says. Not
exactly clear what the logic of that is. כי אמריתה קמיה דשמואל
Ki amritah kamei deShmuel when I said it in front of Shmuel,
אמר זו דברי רבן גמליאל בר רבי amar zo divrei Rabban Gamliel
bar Rabbi that might be the position of Rabban Gamliel bar Rabbi,
אבל חכמים אומרים כדי שיזונו מהן אלו ואלו עד שיבגרו aval chachamim
omrim kedei sheyizonu mehen elu va'elu ad sheyivgaru no,
only if there's enough property enough so that everybody gets supported until
all the girls reach maturity, boys and girls. If
first you make sure that everybody is, again, the girls have a
prior right and a claim to be supported until they reach maturity.
But if there's enough, but even if let's say that's going to
be ten thousand dollars. But okay, then the boys are going to
go have to go begging, that's what the Mishnah says. So if
there's, and
let's say for the boys to be supported also is going to
be another ten thousand dollars. So
what he is saying is until there is twenty thousand dollars in
the estate, then it is not considered under the control of the
boys, because everybody's gotta have food on the table. It only is
considered to fundamentally be under the control of the boys, of the
men, once everybody's food bills are basically covered. But until that point,
then the money is set aside for support and it is not
like the boys inherited and it's under their control. All right, so
let's take a look what the Gemara does with this. עד שיבגרו.
ad sheyivgaru. איתמר נמי עלה itmar nami alah it was also said,
אמר רבין אמר רבי יוחנן ואמרי לה אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן כל שיזונו מהן אלו ואלו עד שיבגרו amar Ravin
amar Rabbi Yochanan ve'amrei lah amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi
Yochanan kol sheyizonu mehen elu va'elu ad sheyivgaru until there's enough money
for all boys and girls and everybody to be supported until the
girls reach maturity. Only when there's more than that amount of money
is it considered like the boys actually inherited an estate. But anything
that's that amount or less, nobody inherited an estate. It's money that
is set aside to pay for everybody's food bills. Okay, so now
the Gemara just says עד שיבגרו. ad sheyivgaru. איתמר נמי עלה אמר
רבין אמר רבי יוחנן ואמרי לה אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן כל שיזונו מהן אלו ואלו עד שיבגרו הן מרובים. itmar
nami alah amar Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan ve'amrei lah amar Rabbah bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan kol sheyizonu mehen elu va'elu ad sheyivgaru
hen merubim. פחות מכאן pachot mikan less than this, הרי אלו מועטים
harei elu muatim again it's considered a small amount. Now the Gemara
just deals with the אלו ואלו. elu va'elu. The way I've been
explaining it is that once you need אלו ואלו elu va'elu boys
and girls before and until that point, it's just money set aside
for people's support. It's not yet considered an estate to be inherited
by the boys. But the Gemara wants to understand that the language
of the Mishnah doesn't exactly fit that. So let's take a look.
But the Gemara says like this, ואי ליכא אלו ואלו ve'ei lika
elu va'elu
עד שיבגרו ad sheyivgaru
and so let's say you know, there's $15,000. $10,000 is enough for
the girls, $5,000 is half as much as what the boys need.
So, and we're calling that נכסים מועטים, nechasim muatim, there's not enough
for both the boys and the girls. What does the משנה say
you do with נכסים מועטים? The משנה says that with נכסים מועטים,
it all goes to the girls and the boys have to go
begging. So the גמרא says that's not so -- is that what
you're saying? If there's 15,000, it all goes to the girls? So
the גמרא says ואי ליכא לאלו ולאלו עד שיבגרו שקלי להו בנות
לכולהו? V'ee leikka l'eilu v'eilu ad sheyibagru shakli lehu banot l'chulhu? The
girls get all 15,000? That's crazy. That doesn't make sense. אלא אמר
רבא, Ella amar Rava, no, no, no, that's not what I meant.
מוציאין להן מזונות לבנות עד שיבגרו. Motzi'in lahen mezonot l'banot ad sheyibagru.
If there's anything less than the 20,000 to support everybody, so there's
only 15,000. So you cordon off the 10,000 needed for the girls
עד שיבגרו, ad sheyibagru, והשאר לבנים, v'hashar l'banim,
and you give the 5,000 for the sons for their support. Okay,
and any more that they need, they'll have to go begging, and
that's what the משנה said. In other words, nobody is saying the
girls get more money than their support. The question again here is
conceptually, do you look at it as if it's money cordoned off
for support, or do you look at it as if it is
the boys inherited the estate and the girls have a lien against
that for their support? So, what we are now saying is, first
you look at all the costs for support for the girls and
the boys until the girls reach an age of maturity, and when
you're up to that amount, we do not look at it like
the boys inherited an estate. It is money cordoned off for support.
What do you do with that money? So, first of all, the
girls have first rights and it all goes to the girls until
their needs are taken care of. If that's 10,000, they get it
all and if there's nothing, the boys go begging. If there's some
extra money, then the boys get the extra money, but they still
have to go begging for the rest. Once there's enough for everybody's
support until the girls get mature and then there's more, then we
say, okay, now we're really talking about an estate, not just supporting
the kids, and now the sons inherit and the girls have a
right and a claim against it. Okay, we will end here.